[SPEAKER_00]: What is choice?
[SPEAKER_00]: I was going to say, yeah, what chooses?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why do I tend to this site?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is there attention to the sound?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Asking why, it's the same type of question.
[SPEAKER_01]: I told you, just in our regard to the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why and who chooses and stuff, all those are assumptions based on the fact that you're confused in regard to choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there is choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is attention.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's attention.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there is intention in regard to...
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Uh-huh.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I take it, if I'm aware of myself, plus I'm seeing intention, thoughts, thinking about, I'm going to do this, do that, and I'm also seeing what I'm attending to, seeing attention, that's also a valuable practice, to see that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it is, but...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's separate things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Most likely, that which you think yourself is in that setup, won't be really yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will be your idea of what yourself was at the time when you thought of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because yourself... that's what we meant before.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you are able to choose, will, intend, without inducing sense of I am, through that choice, will or intention,
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you'll be another one.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, on the way to be one.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why, again, mindfulness of reading ānāpānasati is taught to sotāpannas.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nobody shorter than that can really understand it and do it properly.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if there is a right view, then bringing that sense of, I am choosing, I am willing, I am doing it like this, I'm doing it like that,
[SPEAKER_01]: makes you include yourself always and not exclude and make it kind of disappear in the background.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, that mindfulness and that discernment applies to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what you want to do, you have to... you can't just directly start seeing yourself choosing, because yourself will step outside of that and take it as yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, it won't be your sense of self, it will be elsewhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what you want to do is
[SPEAKER_01]: Recognize the inevitability of the choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to go the indirect way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Realize that, well, you can but not choose.
[SPEAKER_01]: And whatever you do, that's choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're actually not free in regard to choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might be free to choose what you want particularly, but you can't... you're not free to not choose at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's... in that recognition, that's what it's... the kind of... it contains
[SPEAKER_01]: The understanding that even the most volitional act and choice cannot be actually taken as yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they fully depend upon... well, they're given beforehand, as the actual thing, as the possibilities.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't choose something out of nothingness.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's only the implicit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if it's a random spontaneous act,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's implicit as such, and that's why you could have attended it and choose to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Chosen to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, indirectly, you have to kind of hollow it out, so to speak, until the thing is not being fed anymore through the false assumption, through the wrong assumption of, I am choosing this.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, yeah, the choice remains, the preferences remain,
[SPEAKER_01]: But they're not being fed anymore and they don't spread, they don't proliferate through ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like a palm stump.
[SPEAKER_01]: You destroy the roots.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not modifying choices, you're not trimming the branches, landscaping your tree or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You recognize the problem is in the roots.
[SPEAKER_01]: They are feeding this whole proliferation of that tree.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you kill the roots.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, whatever's
[SPEAKER_01]: Whichever way it evolves and grows, it stays.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the point is, it won't go further.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter how it stayed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why our arms can still have habits and stuff like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: External habits.
[SPEAKER_01]: But none of it is being fueled and fed through the roots of greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you're fully aware, mindful of your body again,
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're mindful of the body as a thing out there in the world, because of which your whole experience right now exists, and any choice you make, without actually making any specific choice, is then included in that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You realize that, no matter how far your awareness and mindfulness go, it will always remain determined by this living body out there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if the body is dead, this cannot stand.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that already includes the nature of the choice within that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to start like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: When that view gets established, then you have to kind of go within that and clear out all the residues inside.
[SPEAKER_01]: But first, you have to start from the outside, which is why Sotāpanna still has conceit and so on, that he needs to kind of purify later.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he doesn't have that general, fundamental, wrong view.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the starting point is that
[SPEAKER_01]: The general experience as a whole is seen determined by the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, you recognize, as we spoke before, that that body would not be even discernible as such, if there is no general experience in consciousness in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not that just everything stands upon the body and the body is out there in the world independent.
[SPEAKER_01]: That body out there in the world is actually determined.
[SPEAKER_01]: But this mind depends upon that body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, loosely put, obviously.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nāma-rūpa, viññāṇa, viññāṇa, nāma-rūpa.
[SPEAKER_01]: But as I said before, it's that matter out in the world, with the consciousness out there, with that matter, that your experience exists as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: Consciousness is not in your head, or anything like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's equally external, out there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, you know, it's a bit... conscience is out there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where matter is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you discern consciousness based on where matter is discerned to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that actual matter is inaccessible.
[SPEAKER_01]: As I said before, when you think of the four elements, well, that's your thought that stands for that which four elements is.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it actually stands for
[SPEAKER_01]: What the nature of the four great elements is, means you're not conceiving them.
[SPEAKER_01]: That thought is the correct thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, you have understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, they don't find a footing in your experience anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can say the four great elements have ceased in another end.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if your thought, the presentation, or dhamma, or phenomena, whatever you want to call it, stands for something that's assumed to be matter, in other words, stands wrongly,
[SPEAKER_01]: This represents that which is matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: That means, ah, you have conceived it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have conceived the matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: The matter found Fuji.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why the whole world exists for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is more of a reality.
[SPEAKER_00]: But knowing that whatever I think is only a thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that matter is unthinkable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Knowing that what you think is only a thought, and the matter is unthinkable, and knowing that also is a thought, that doesn't stand for that matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that matter, that I just said, is also thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, any possibility, and the more and more peripheral, the peripheral thought in regard to your current thought, doesn't stand for that matter anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not just actual thought, but the whole nature of peripheral thought doesn't represent it either.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you can say you have fully approached conceivings.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't conceive it in any shape or form.
[SPEAKER_01]: Far, near, direct, indirect, anyhow.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then saying, well, so it's all in my head.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would that again?
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: In a way, it is all in your head.
[SPEAKER_01]: But would your head be there, if you're not discerning it, if you're not thinking of it as my head?
[SPEAKER_01]: It wouldn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you recognize, well, would I be even able to think any of that, if this body, this material body out there, is not living and breathing?
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, yeah, it's all in your head, for as long as your body is alive.
[SPEAKER_01]: The body is destroyed, the matter is taken away, there is no more head, there is no more mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, recognize, well, actually, my mind, the experience as a whole, not
[SPEAKER_01]: Imaginary, mental, whatever, doesn't, it doesn't actually, it's not independent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, and that's usually what statement, it's all in my head, implies.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, me, and everything else, kind of, basically, I'm the most fundamental.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you recognize, sure, I am mostly fundamental, and then you take that thought, and recognize it as determined by the fact that matter is there, inaccessible.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you know, you can know that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if something happens to that matter, everything's gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can know that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you know that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, knowing that long enough will bring further recognition.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, even if you have a thought control in my head, you don't take that as me and mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you know that's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, everything is thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the thought, the nature of thought, is able to manifest itself because matter is there, present, alive.
[SPEAKER_01]: That gets destroyed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is another thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's another thought in regard to the method that's present alive, while I'm still alive.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is another thought, which is another thought, which... And yeah, it's infinite.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no end, because you can never reach the matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: But through that infinity, if you want to pursue it or not, you can know, okay, I'm able to go in this any infinite direction for as long as that which is matter stays.
[SPEAKER_01]: If that which is matter gets destroyed, the whole infinity is gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is what I meant when I said
[SPEAKER_01]: How will I put it?
[SPEAKER_01]: When eternal, infinite, is not confused with permanent and self.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because infinite, it's like eternity.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can go forever, for as long as the matter stands.
[SPEAKER_01]: The matter is removed, the whole domain is gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: It almost sounds like I'm going to have to convince myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, in a way, you do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why it has to be taken on artificially, like a graph, as Nibbāla said, the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, if you do it long enough, because, or if, you took it rightly, and if it corresponds to the way things actually are, then, yeah, it will take the proper route, and then you can see it for yourself as being confirmed.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you won't see it naturally, because that would mean you could find your own way out of ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you have to take the right conviction.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, there is the assumption, in every kutujana, in different degrees, that things will happen naturally.
[SPEAKER_01]: You practice, and then you feel this thing unraveling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, oh, it happened.
[SPEAKER_01]: I got it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, it's clear.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those are kind of very general descriptions, but they're usually taken to mean a wrong thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want it to happen.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want enlightenment to be found.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, it's all an easy ride afterwards.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to convince yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, well, it's not real, if I convince myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, what makes you think that your criteria, what's real, what's not real, is correct?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, Pratyujana thinks it's real.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's his self.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he might not go so crudely and think, oh, I am, I'm eternal or whatever, but still, for as long as he knows he's put to it in the human, he thinks, this is real, that's not real, means, ah, this is more important, that's less important, means, I don't actually know important as important, unimportant as unimportant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why that was like the Sotāpanna, that verse says, knowing important is important, unimportant is unimportant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Getting that criteria.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you get criteria,
[SPEAKER_01]: If you convince yourself to such an extent, the recognition takes place.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, there is a form of natural unravelling then, but not before.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why, as I said, the Buddha would always make such exclamations like,
[SPEAKER_01]: I've done it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nobody else had any input.
[SPEAKER_01]: No luck, no circumstances.
[SPEAKER_01]: I've made the effort and I got it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I worked through this conviction until I've seen it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now I'm sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: I had faith that the conviction was right, so I was convincing myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, I've seen it and it's right.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't need to convince myself anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I certainly don't have faith.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have confidence, because I know that it's right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sounds insane.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sounds fundamental.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sounds fundamentalist.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sounds like mad.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is exactly how Buddha saw it the first time, when he met that ascetic.
[SPEAKER_01]: He says, I am self-enlightened.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nobody.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm like absolutely no teacher.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm the greatest.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm this.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And this man said, so be it, friend, and walked off.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it was all true, what he said.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, obviously, then he realized, well, if I want to teach, I need to find a slightly more relatable approach that will not induce, kind of, resistance in people, thinking you're all conceited.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's all, it's all fact.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sotāpanna, that what we had on the, on the, on the monument in Skraut, I've gone beyond the witherings of the view.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am my own guide.
[SPEAKER_01]: Cannot be, cannot be guided.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not even I don't want to.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's impossible for me to be guided by another.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it's that level.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, that's just fundamentalist.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's just... that's just wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's just fixed view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Every view is a fixed view.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to get the right fix.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to make sure that
[SPEAKER_01]: Your convictions are correct, or as correct as they can be.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you really want to emphasize the discernment, reasoning, reflection.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, as you can see, you don't really know what you're convincing yourself, whether it's right or wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's right, you'll recognize it as right.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will correspond to the right things, and then you'll see through it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you ain't, it means you're just going to wind yourself further and further and further into the ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, it's a very risky thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you're ignorant anyway.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, not trying it is even more foolish than at least attempting to bring it out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like when people are afraid to commit the view, like, oh, I don't hold any fixed views.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's a fixed view for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: That you refuse responsibility for.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's even worse.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a point of freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is a form of measuring.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you start practicing, yeah, there are some tokens and little hints.
[SPEAKER_01]: There can be, okay, I might be on the right way.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why we'll explain the four stages and the factors that are relevant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through reviewing those, you get the pointers.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, am I free from doubt?
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I free from self-view?
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I free from holding on to virtue and duty?
[SPEAKER_01]: Keep reviewing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Understanding what those are means you'll be free from that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But also to keep in mind that those are the things that are causing suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, no, holding on to the self-view is what causes suffering, what makes you liable to suffering of various kinds.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you wouldn't be able to say, well, you're kind of trying to practice, look at these things, look at these things, and then one day say, well,
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm... is it working?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I'm happy enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm happier than I was.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but are you satisfied?
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know, but I'm happier.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means you settled for less, or basically settled for nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you would know
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, basically, putujana is in a train that's about to crash.
[SPEAKER_01]: And sotāpati takes you out of the crash altogether.
[SPEAKER_01]: What you just referred to, well, I'm happier, means, oh, you just got upgraded in a fancy compartment.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still gonna crash.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, ultimately, it absolutely makes no difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: What you want to be is out of that train.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's something that you would know.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's something you would know, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you have doubt in regard to it, it means, ah, you're not free from doubt, which means that you're definitely not free from that factor, which means you cannot be so far.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, so you can get people who get so convinced of themselves, but it's easy to undo that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, you would see the need, like, you know, no, no, I understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just to challenge a view or two of this, and you'll see the need to maintain the great point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's, it's, it's existential dependence.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, but then, you can't really do much for them, because if they're able to convince themselves to that extent, believe something that they're not, means they're, like, deeply rooted into bad faith.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the authenticity has to be the first point.
[SPEAKER_01]: You really want to do it for yourself, and completely, like, nobody else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Really, for me, concerning only me,
[SPEAKER_01]: So, lying to yourself, just so that others will recognize you as such, or lying to yourself through the others, by others blaming you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, that's just obscuring the basic one.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you will know.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will know what you're doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you're honest in that level, you wouldn't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Suffering and freedom from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the goal.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the criteria.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the measurement.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing else is accepted as compromise.
[SPEAKER_01]: I told you that when I was back in Serbia, and then, you know, you go on and you get all sorts of Buddhist books and texts or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was reading everything, and I came across, and then, you know, Sotāpanna and Sakadāgāmī and contemplating all that, and then I came across this IKM article, where she says about Sotāpatti.
[SPEAKER_01]: I went, oh, great, because I was just looking for anyone's input.
[SPEAKER_01]: I want to learn more.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think that was before, actually, yeah, way before I came across Nyanavira.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, and she said, oh, we are, basically, we are already Sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's great.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're very fortunate.
[SPEAKER_01]: And my first thought was, wow, I'm Sotāpanna then.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I continue reading and she says,
[SPEAKER_01]: She explains how we have self-awareness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, basically, we all know that bowing to the shrines and statues is meaningless.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, we are all free from rites and rituals.
[SPEAKER_01]: Are we?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Show of hands.
[SPEAKER_01]: We are.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, we all know that the Buddha was right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, we have no doubt in regard to his teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: He is our teacher.
[SPEAKER_01]: We accept him.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, we're free from doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we all know that self doesn't really exist.
[SPEAKER_01]: Modern science has proven the molecules are constantly changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no substance to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, we agree.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, we are all sotāpānas.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, we're thinking, okay, I'm a sotāpāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, immediately, next thought, well, what difference does it make?
[SPEAKER_01]: If that's what sotāpāna is, what difference does that make?
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't care.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because I wasn't concerned about becoming a sotāpāna or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was concerned about being suffering and free from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, sure, you can have the whole Buddhist world recognize you as a sotāpāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're internally not free from suffering, it's irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unless,
[SPEAKER_01]: You were never actually about freedom from suffering, but you were about recognition of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You felt lonely, felt inadequate, or your daddy never loved you, or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you have to be honest with yourself and practice for the right reasons.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_01]: The dhamma has only one taste.
[SPEAKER_01]: Same like the sea has a taste of salt, dhamma has a taste of freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can't do it for any other reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: And why would you?
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's exactly the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, well, yeah, okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: According to this, I'm an athān.
[SPEAKER_01]: What difference does it make?
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where my concern is, and that's where my efforts are applied to.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, obviously, you read what the Buddha said, and Sotāpanna is one who is free from suffering to a great deal, and those that were scared from prana but choose to be jinn are quiet, and it was wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, okay, so if she was wrong, means that the views that she used to describe these three fetters are also wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, okay, so what does really freedom from virtue and duty mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because clearly, if what I think it means, unless that thought makes me so dependent, means that thought is wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's what I meant when I said, by understanding what the fetters are, you abandon them.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no discrepancy.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no delay.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what would you say, then, free from virtue and duty?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, for as long as you think that you're good virtue and a sense of duty, I'm a monk, I need to meditate, I need to do this, any, like the nature of duty, the nature of virtue, as long as you think, as long as you hold that to pertain to the practice, means you're holding on to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because dhamma is completely different from that.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no room for virtue in dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no dhamma without virtue, but virtue is not the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: As they said themselves, when they were saying, what should we recite first?
[SPEAKER_01]: Stories concerning sīla or the stories concerning the dhamma?
[SPEAKER_01]: They said, well, there is no dhamma without sīla, so let's let's let's recite that first, and then they recited the sutta to be taken after.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they knew the dhamma is not that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's almost
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, what does that mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: I can go and do everything?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't do everything which you want.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wholesome or unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because saying that dhamma is not virtue is not like saying dhamma is un-virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there a word un-virtue?
[SPEAKER_01]: Un-virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you say that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Anyway, you get the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's people's assumption.
[SPEAKER_01]: Good means dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you say, no, there's no room for good in dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, dhamma is bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, there's no room for bad either.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what means dropping, sīla, bhakti, dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: People usually translate it as rites and rituals.
[SPEAKER_01]: Place it down.
[SPEAKER_01]: It kind of makes you... enables you to relate to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, bowing to a shrine doesn't mean anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's much subtler than that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if bowing, if stopping, if not bowing to a shrine, is required to bend the fetter, well, most of the monks, well, many more, would have been sotāpannas.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's subtler than that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's actually sīla, pata, paramāsa.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's sīla.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same word.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a different meaning.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: Virtue and duty.
[SPEAKER_01]: He goes again with trying to purify...
[SPEAKER_01]: But there is no dhamma without virtue and duty.
[SPEAKER_01]: But dhamma is not virtue, do you?
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe you have to restrain yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to restrain yourself first, and then you might see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when you see it, you'll see that it's not the restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not restrained either.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you can never... if you just restrain, restrain, restrain, you'll always be restraining yourself, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there's no point... or is there?
[SPEAKER_00]: A point where you restrain so much, where you can never... you're so virtuous, you don't think anything
[SPEAKER_01]: And that won't result in dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because people think, if I'm just virtuous enough, I'll see the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not necessarily.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you don't put anything on that basis, it remains just a basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what's your end restraint?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like a raft.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you don't use a raft, it doesn't mean anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I suppose, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, it can... like, but I think I said that before.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like a fertile field, but if you don't put any seeds, it's just a fertile field.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't expect, you know, ripening the fruit.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is an ant, because you have planted it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, eating the fruit, yeah, you can say that you wouldn't be there without a field, but it's certainly not the soil and the field, because you're eating only the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: They wouldn't be there without a field, but it's clearly not the field.
[SPEAKER_00]: How long does it take to become virtuous?
[SPEAKER_01]: As long as it's necessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, some people can do it, you know, in a half a night.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some people, like, again, some people can do it just after speaking with Buddha for a while.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind will be virtuous enough for them to get the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's because they don't have the right instruction without any kind of frequency notions obstructing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, virtue is not just restraint?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the restraint is supposed to bring the state of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is the virtue state of mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Virtue is a network like behavior and attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like a recognition.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: I've been engaging in virtuous behavior.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a recognition.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it does take time.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you can get, yeah, to, as I said,
[SPEAKER_01]: Some people can get established upon that recognition quickly, upon one virtuous act.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some people need more.
[SPEAKER_01]: Today, I think, most people need much more.
[SPEAKER_01]: Much more time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, much more of virtuous acts in order to get the recognition of a phenomenon of virtue which you're established upon.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, if you do practice dhamma, that goes in a completely different direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you weren't, means you could do
[SPEAKER_01]: The dhamma means there would be set of prescribed rites, rituals, duties, methods, techniques, vipassana retreats that could lead you to the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: A mere performance, mechanical performance of something, could lead you to the dhamma, but it can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because dhamma doesn't pretend to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why does virtue... why does virtue have to be the base?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is that question relevant?
[SPEAKER_01]: Anyway, I can answer it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Back onto the simile of going out on a motorway,
[SPEAKER_01]: In pursuing your senses, in exposing yourself to accidents or a chopping block or whatever else, say no to it by default.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it better than saying yes?
[SPEAKER_01]: If there is a danger involved in it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's better to say no.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's better to restrain.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why virtue is better.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you don't know why, but through doing it, it prevents.
[SPEAKER_01]: It prevents the more immediate demise.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you know there's trouble in that regard you get, if you don't restrain yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Things that could happen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it goes... it doesn't just concern the bodily behavior.
[SPEAKER_01]: It goes down to the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: It works same for the mind, just subtler, but it's the same principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: By letting mind go onto the domain that doesn't own, you're taken by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: By saying no, means you remain out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: By remaining out of it means you can see it eventually.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not if you're engaged.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what Buddha meant when he said there is no... it's impossible to engage in a sensual act without having your mind being taken by those sensual perceptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I'm free from sensuality, yet I'm doing sensual acts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Based on reality, it's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just cannot... cannot occur.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why.
[SPEAKER_01]: A person who is not virtuous, then,
[SPEAKER_01]: It means their minds are assumed in those domains.
[SPEAKER_01]: They can't get a perspective on it, if he is in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when your general behavior is not engaging in things that are compromising the perspective on your general behavior, you can start seeing that the, well, simultaneous kind of
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by restraining first, in order to get a perspective, you get a perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you see the place of restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: You see the place of duty, which means you don't hold on to it blindly anymore, which means you're free from sīla-vād-vādanāsa.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, anyway, you don't have to restrain that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you will, because that's now the established normal behavior.
[SPEAKER_01]: And also, because you recognize it's more less hassle and more pleasant to be restrained.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like the joy of renunciation replaces the joy of sensual indulgence.
[SPEAKER_01]: But to get any further, you have to...
[SPEAKER_01]: It is our view for that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't just do pure restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, you can be telling yourself, but it won't take root, because it's not enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you get that general perspective, and you see that whatever choice you make, made, will make, your general experience, your experience as a whole,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's fully dependent upon this random physical body right here, right now, that's the most close to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, there's this body, there are these bodies.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no difference between them.
[SPEAKER_01]: They are bodies.
[SPEAKER_01]: In those bodies, they're internally, externally, internally and externally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Bodies are there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just that this particular body is closer to the general experience as a whole, determines it more than these bodies.
[SPEAKER_01]: But none of it can be mine to begin with.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, getting that kind of perspective means good or bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: Good and bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: Neutral.
[SPEAKER_01]: Both.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's impermanent, because it's within that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Cannot escape.
[SPEAKER_01]: Cannot spill over.
[SPEAKER_01]: Cannot step outside.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's completely different than just doing good.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's absolutely nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You abandon good, inasmuch you abandon bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in order to do so, you need to be established upon good.
[SPEAKER_01]: And why is it good?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because at least you don't know why, but by doing good, not bad, means at least you kind of don't step into that domain where you fully lose control, fully lose perspective, fully take it back.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't take the bait, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it says no to... you don't even know that it's bait, but by adopting an attitude of saying no to it, you don't take it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And later on, you find out that there is actually poison in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a simile
[SPEAKER_01]: I just wish you'd understand that the poisonous drink, in terms of the sensual pleasure, pleasant, pleasing in every sense, sight, smell, texture, everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you know now that there is a poison to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because in the beginning, why am I saying no to this?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's innocent.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's nice.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: The whole world does it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why do I have to say no?
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't know that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you would, you would be free from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you take it and trust it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's better to say no.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you ask, why is it better?
[SPEAKER_01]: And I say, because you don't consume it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just... you don't know why it's better not to consume it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Later on, when you find out, you can find out only because you haven't been consuming it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's effortless to restrain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Afterwards, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: After there is no restraint, it's understanding, which is why I cannot engage in a sexual intercourse or any sensual act.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's not restraining himself, really, kind of trying hard enough to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: He can't even conceive to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why it's better not to do it in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, afterwards, it becomes self-evident.
[SPEAKER_01]: The sotāpanna sees that, though he still is... Yeah, he sees that in general, on a fundamental level, but more particularly, he still has worries.
[SPEAKER_01]: He still has... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you can fall back into those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: To an extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't fall back to the point of having a wrong view of Atharvāda anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why, at most, seven rebirths.
[SPEAKER_01]: But remember that sutta, sometimes it's the second one, that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or the third one, that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Seven at most, but not necessarily all seven.
[SPEAKER_01]: One becomes, upon landing, in all those different turns slightly,
[SPEAKER_01]: Slightly ambiguous descriptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he doesn't even get fully born as human.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just upon landing, to be reborn, whatever that means, he becomes, he becomes an anant.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the parents reborn doesn't need much to remember again?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, he might, he might not, like, he doesn't remember, he might not remember particular things,
[SPEAKER_01]: But the principles that pertain to the nature of memory are there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he just needs to be alive.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if he's not, well, in the next life, then the next life, at most seven lifetimes, and those principles will kind of seep back into whatever understanding he has.
[SPEAKER_02]: Probably he's very naturally inclined towards the world's teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, naturally inclined means, basically, those principles are what he is, so...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it will, inevitably, because that's the direction here.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whether he wants to go this way, he'll be going that way, eventually.
[SPEAKER_01]: And no matter how indulgent he can get, and careless, it's all, like, just nothing in comparison.
[SPEAKER_01]: He will arrive there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, yeah, there is still some work to be done, so there's no excuse for not doing it, which is why the body would be urgent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so, I've been saying, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm trying to gain the perspective, eh... that this general awareness is... depends on this... these particulars, body.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then doing it, and then seeing that
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you're not entirely free from suffering, but there's a major shift.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're no longer subject to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then you have no doubts, in regard to what you've been doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: At the same, you know, once it works, so there's the effect of the karma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Once that's worked.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you can't even conceive.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any idea of a cameo existing upon anywhere else, different from your general experience as a whole, dependent upon these material organs, which is also part of general experience as a whole, as a form of designation, these organs.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not to change the
[SPEAKER_00]: In general awareness, how does that happen?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just an attention to the whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's not happening.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's already there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You step back, you recognize it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only reason you can reflect is because there are... the nature of reflection is possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: If there wouldn't be a place...
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not something I'm doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not something... Well, you do it by intending to go that direction, but that direction exists.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what your experience is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, general and particular, actual and peripheral, peripheral being general, that's already there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just that you're so used to being absorbed in what's taking your attention actually, right now, directly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't see peripheral, then you wonder how this peripheral comes... No, that peripheral is the basis for actual.
[SPEAKER_01]: And in the same sense, that peripheral is determined by that which is not peripheral.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, it's peripheral to this.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, recognizing the phenomenon of that peripheral means developing mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like learning how to see without shifting your vision directly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Learning how to see peripherally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if I'm trying to do it, it doesn't really work, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, yeah, if you try to do it, if you intend it, or rather over-intend it, in this case, means you just shift onto a new actual, which means now peripheral is different, and you're not seeing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you see it in regard to what you're seeing, which is a form of seeing, an indirect way of seeing, which is an equally valid way of seeing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just got so used to
[SPEAKER_01]: The norm of existence and reality.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, if something is not there, well, it doesn't exist.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's unreal.
[SPEAKER_00]: And general awareness is that the... what is another term for it?
[SPEAKER_01]: What do you mean?
[SPEAKER_00]: I say, reflect... Mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mindfulness is present.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's conscious.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mindfulness is established.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you don't establish it by going somewhere deep inside of your head or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: You establish it by recognizing your general experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right now, you speak fully determined by this positioned matter of your body on that chair, while we're speaking, while you're asking these questions.
[SPEAKER_01]: That body remains there, seated, for whichever, whichever situation it's in.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you have no control over the material aspect of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, you have no control to such an extent that you can't even think matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can think in regard to that which matter is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even that which you think that matter is, in regard to which you're thinking, that's also a thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how inaccessible elements are.
[SPEAKER_01]: And consciousness is out there with them, equally inaccessible.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you will realize that whatever comes as a result of conscious matter, namely feeling, perception, intentions, are equally inaccessible.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, my sense of myself, me, volition, intention, determination are not mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Inconceivable to be mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is... remember we spoke about it a few days ago.
[SPEAKER_01]: We said when it's so fundamentally inconceivable, death is like... it's absolutely nothing to grieve over.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's impossible to even conceive a notion of grief, sadness over it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why, in that Udana, the Buddha said, there is the unborn, the undetermined, all of those, like there is, and that's that inaccessible thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if there wouldn't be, nibbāna is the inaccessible.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's real.
[SPEAKER_01]: In every experience, in the experience of a Buddhist, non-Buddhist, patujana, arahant, nibbāna is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just whether it's fully understood or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: If there wouldn't be inaccessible, means access would be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And freedom from it would not be possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: But because there is inaccessible, freedom from anything that you could have accessed before, is possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: And accessible is anything that appears.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means you can access it, you can take it, you can appropriate it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, birth, aging, death, and so on, as a result of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you fully understand that it's rooted
[SPEAKER_01]: Upon something you can't even think.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you know that, means you know what inaccessible is, without conceiving it in your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's absolutely, like, no room for emotion.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why one doesn't feel anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how, as well, you can resolve upon that, with wisdom, long enough to become an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you keep that image long enough, correctly, without conceiving it, all of the factors will fall away.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is what the seeker is supposed to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not me, not mine, not I am.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not existing here, not existing there, not assuming I exist like this, not assuming I exist like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what the element of nibbāna,
[SPEAKER_01]: Like nibbāna dāt, that's what it means.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's there as a possibility, as an element, but it needs to be understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, to get established.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it needs to be understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't... and that's why you can conceive it as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: In that other sutta, it says, he thinks, oh, I am in nibbāna, I am entering nibbāna, and that, which he refers to, is actually nibbāna, but he's not entering it or attaining it, because he's thinking, I am.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's conceiving it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's nothing magical.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's nothing hidden, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, what you have is patuji's five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: What shows that it's five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's within that, that the whole dhamma is contained.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, it pertains to the way you take them, or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: The five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you take them, for as long as you don't fully understand that, eh... that it is impossible to take them in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're inaccessible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not knowing that they're inaccessible, you access them, through that lack of knowledge.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is no room for it, but it has always been there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's beginningless, but actually, it's not supposed to be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not needed.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not necessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a parasite, as they refer to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But beginningless.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's something you knew before, because if you knew before, you couldn't have fallen onto this not knowing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because once you know, you cannot not know anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this lack of knowledge is beginningless, yet completely gratuitous.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not knowing that they're inaccessible.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: With general mindfulness, we can begin to recognize that khandhas are inaccessible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you recognize that any thought, any notion, any talking, any designation, no matter how subtle, how immoral, how general, how ambiguous, you recognize it as such, and by recognizing it as such, you don't take it to stand, you don't take it to access that which is inaccessible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is back onto the principle of meditation I was telling you about before.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever arises, you include it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You recognize it as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you say, ah, the matter is inaccessible, that thought of that inaccessible matter is also your thought, which you then think that matter to be, so that matter has access to you, or you access the matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: So he conceives in matter, matter in me, I am in matter, I am left, I am right.
[SPEAKER_01]: He conceives matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you know that matter is inaccessible, and then that thought doesn't stand for that which matter is, and that thought that says that which matter is also doesn't stand for that which matter is, and there's no end to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you leave the whole infinite kind of domain as a... well, sorry, you don't leave it, but you kind of understand that whole infinite domain as basically inaccessible.
[SPEAKER_01]: It cannot access matter, matter cannot access it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No matter how far you go, what next thought comes, it cannot stand for that which matter is, because that's another thought that can stand for what matter is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you realize, whatever I think, quickly or slowly, ambiguously, it will be on the level of thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, that which matter is cannot manifest itself in my soul, because what I think are my thoughts, which is why what I perceive and my perception, what I feel are my feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't feel my thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't perceive my feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: That confusion means confusion in regard to the basic nature of phenomena.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it needs to be clarified to that point, when what I'm saying now can make more sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, if you think matter, you direct your mind to matter, that's a thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: You recognize it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No matter how far it goes, you recognize it within the domain of thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Next thought,
[SPEAKER_01]: Still shares the same nature of thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you get to understand that when you start concerning yourself with nature of things, as opposed to with particularity of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't care what you think, you care thought is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't care what you see, you care sight is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You start recognizing the nature of things by being established in a nature of thought, nature of the thought domain, which is basically nature of everything, means whatever you think will be seen
[SPEAKER_01]: In its nature, which means, it will be seen as rising, ceasing, and persisting while changing, for as long as it's persisting.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it will not be confused, it will not be assumed to stand for that which is outside of the domain of thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even the thought outside of the domain of thought cannot actually be outside of the domain of thought, because it's also another thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you can't step outside of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wow.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll be mindful of that nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to recognize, you have to at the same time see this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: It arises on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: You didn't create that thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you recognize it to the extent which has arisen, you're not adding anything to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no assumption to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not taking anything away from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why, by contemplating Sotāpanna, or even the Bodhisattva, previous Buddha Vipassana, before he became the Buddha,
[SPEAKER_01]: He recognized that, and then all he'd done was contemplating arising, manifesting, arising, appearance, and disappearance, persisting or changing in regard to five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things in there arising, things manifesting in there arising, things manifesting in there ceasing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: He'd done that long enough, he became samsambuddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the same principle works for anybody who wants to become an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because things do arise on their own.
[SPEAKER_01]: If they weren't, it means you would be their master.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's... if I recognize feeling, I say that's just a thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, feeling is mental.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you say that's just a thought, as opposed to what else?
[SPEAKER_01]: What else is not just a thought?
[SPEAKER_01]: Even just a thought is just a thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's what I like.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's... well, everything is a thought, then.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, instead of it's just a thought, no, that's a thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, mastering your thoughts, you'll be an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, funnily enough, there is a sutra that says that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you don't master your abstract scholarly proliferation thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: You master the phenomenon of thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because everything is mental in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't be able to discern anything if it
[SPEAKER_01]: If it doesn't, kind of, pertain to your mind, it might come from different directions, but that's where you know it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just couldn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, feeling is mental.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you say, whatever arises is... Well, mental means it's phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what mind is.
[SPEAKER_01]: The domain of the phenomenon is what citta is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when the Buddha asked, well, what are those dhammas?
[SPEAKER_01]: What else can it be?
[SPEAKER_01]: What are the sankhāras?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: What else can it be?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you use thought to describe your discursive thinking,
[SPEAKER_01]: Proliferation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you shouldn't use the same word to describe this.
[SPEAKER_01]: You could refer to it as a phenomenon or a mental image.
[SPEAKER_01]: And everything is a mental image.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise, you wouldn't be able to discern it as anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would not manifest.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the mental image of this is just thought, is a mental image.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of this is just a thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, thoughts are mental images.
[SPEAKER_01]: Perceptions are mental images.
[SPEAKER_01]: Feelings are mental images.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thoughts are dhammas.
[SPEAKER_01]: Feelings are dhammas.
[SPEAKER_01]: Perceptions are dhammas.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thoughts are dhammas.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So contemplating arising and falling, you're contemplating arising and falling of mental images.
[SPEAKER_01]: The experience has all its foundations.
[SPEAKER_01]: It has arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, arising is already persisting while changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just increasing in its presence.
[SPEAKER_01]: But increase, like fading in, means, ah, it's already changing while it's increasing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the three are arising, persisting, sorry, arising, ceasing, and persisting while changing, fully understood, and so on, what the suttas talk about.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like three things in a sequence.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's certainly not what Bhikkhu Bodhi and many others say, like, arising, persisting, or changing, ceasing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's like a linear observation of something that fully pertains to time, something you can measure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, it started, now it's lasting, now it's gone, and I'm fully out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Arising is already persisting or changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ceasing is already persisting or changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's just like fading in and fading out while persisting or changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's on two completely different levels.
[SPEAKER_01]: Arising and ceasing is on one level, persisting or changing is on another level.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that already means you cannot not include yourself in that form of contemplation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if your general experience as a whole is arising in a certain way, it's persisting or changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you're aware of that, well, you're aware of you being within that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, this is arising for me, or to me, or left of me, or right of me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's all persisting or changing, and you're mindful of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, in the same sense, when something is fading away, it's still there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still a form of appearance.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't find impermanence at the ending of the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's just another thing there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll find it within the appearance, within the persistence of that thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll find that's why it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it possesses on its own.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just woke up.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can practice this whole thing in regard to your own body right here, right now, whichever position it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because when you think, oh, my body is seated,
[SPEAKER_01]: You think that stands for that matter which your body is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's already a form of conceiving.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to have a thought, because you can't but not think.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to have a thought that my body is still seated, but then you want to leave that thought to be to the extent that it wants to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, you have to recognize it phenomenologically, the way it has arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you do, then it will not be conceiving that because of which that thought is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is the four great elements.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why I was writing the term indetermination, that because of which, because if I use the direct term, people would just think, ah, that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But no.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's another thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: By saying that because of which that thought is, standing for that because of which that thought is, means, oh, you just conceived that matter because of which your thought is, including the idea of what that matter is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just think of your body posture, but don't think that to be that element that... because of which your body posture is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, leave, or rather imply, that matter as inaccessible.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, when your thoughts are, that matter is inaccessible, that is not accessing it either, that thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you peripherally become more mindful.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't have to think about anything else, really, in terms of collecting all the data and information and
[SPEAKER_01]: mapping it all out, it's it's right here.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, remain mindful of the four body postures correctly, without them assuming the four great elements, without your material organs standing for that, because of which those material organs are, and you will not access that matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, you'll be you'll be knowing it, so to speak, because you know
[SPEAKER_01]: That this body, this experience as a whole, is determined, then, because of which it's already there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, if it weren't determined, it wouldn't have been here, already arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then you stop assuming the existence of those determinations.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is another way of saying, you stop having those thoughts then, standing for that because of which your thoughts were in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what it means, the cessation of all the saṅkharas.
[SPEAKER_01]: The determinations don't exist anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing to determine, because there's nothing to access in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's interesting.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bodily posture.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just when I say bodily posture.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: The image of my body.
[SPEAKER_00]: The sight of my body sitting here.
[SPEAKER_01]: What does every posture have in common?
[SPEAKER_01]: What does the image of every posture have in common?
[SPEAKER_01]: The image of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why we can just be mindful of the bodies there to the extent necessary for the final knowledge.
[SPEAKER_01]: But obviously, posture in itself is generally enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, yeah, it's not the fundamental.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the reason why it's good to think of posture, because it will keep that mental element, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it will... it will kind of allow you to not become fully complacent in conceiving
[SPEAKER_01]: The image of your body is there, which your body is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because posture is sort of a designation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's a shape, it's a position of your body, but it's also a designation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Citta, or mental designation, which means, oh, it's always there, because even knowing the body to the extent necessary for the mind, well, that image of the body is already a mental designation.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's... that's... that was never the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just... Well, the problem was when that designation stood for that because of which that designation was in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: Stood for matter, stood for... stood for the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why you take up five aggregates like the fire takes up its fuel.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they... they don't need you.
[SPEAKER_01]: They completely exist without you anyway.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or you can just be even less particular and be mindful of your bodily posture while you're doing other things and then just regard that image of your bodily posture upon which you're anchored, mindful, as subject to destruction and you can't do anything about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that image is genuinely subject to destruction and that image is genuinely the determination for your whatever else particular things you're doing while you're mindful of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means whatever you're doing, while you're mindful of that which is subject to destruction, you won't fully appropriate.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will remain mindful of.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if I tell you, okay, well, you go walk about in your day, do stuff, but at any... at the next minute, there might be a bullet flying through your brain from some direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, so you will be going about your business eventually.
[SPEAKER_01]: This will always be in the back of your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're subject to that, because if you were not subject to that, it wouldn't be possible for that even to arise as a possibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's contemplation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by... exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: By contemplating right things, correct things, as impermanent, and suffering, you will abandon everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not by just applying blame.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, it's all impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's all... that's irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_01]: What you want to see as impermanent,
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't mean that you see it's destruction, because if you were to see destruction on your body, well, you wouldn't see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll be destroyed.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to see it as subject to destruction, which means it's there, it's manifested, it's present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because of that, it's subject to being destroyed.
[SPEAKER_01]: And seeing things subject to such-and-such means seeing things in their nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, be mindful of general experience as a whole, while you're aware of your body right here, right now, in this particular posture, that is, like, fundamental, kind of, pivotal point of your whole general experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be inconceivable if this body is not alive.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's that simple.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're mindful of that alive body in this particular posture, in that particular posture.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's something that on that level, not on the level of your thoughts, whether you think about it or not, it remains subject to be destroyed.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what it means you think of it on that level.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, oh, whether I think about this or not, even when I forget, it makes no difference to that nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: It remains subjected to destruction.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's in their domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: And nothing you can do about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there will be proper mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: That results in discernment and wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not, you know, be here now and hug a tree and feel good about yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Abandon everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Abandon the shit before it sinks you with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even if things are happening to you too fast, busy, crowd, you can't, like, follow, well, which you're not supposed to do from the beginning, follow things particularly, but be even more aware of what's happening particularly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You still know the body is there, and that's the reason why all these things can happen in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: The body is there, which is subject to destruction and peril, which means, well, whatever is happening right here, right now, is kind of circumstantial.
[SPEAKER_01]: It could have not been.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it certainly will not be.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's another reason why, like, the whole contemporary person is just so wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's completely the opposite direction from what I'm just saying.
[SPEAKER_01]: Instead of looking at the general image of your body, then you're trying to force this kind of constant, actual, direct perception of body moving, moving, touching, touching, sitting, sitting, drinking, drinking, like, absorb, absorb yourself in the moment as hard as you can.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's completely the other way.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't want... Well, you don't bother about being absorbed or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to maintain the background image of a body that determines your absorption or lack of it, that determines it, that body which is subject to destruction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, hence, there's absolutely no method or technique or set of mechanical repetition that can take you in that direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a recognition.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a formal understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so this...
[SPEAKER_00]: I've seen the body there.
[SPEAKER_00]: By discerning the body there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Discerning the body there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's already there.
[SPEAKER_01]: With a general awareness, but seeing that body there is... General awareness already implies the body there, then you discern the body there, as then, because of which, the general awareness is possible in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: But by doing that, I'm including myself there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, well, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: By doing that, you leave no... no... no room for yourself to step outside and be excluded.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you include everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whatever yourself... yourself tries to move, it will be within that room.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can't do that by... by trying to, like, reach the most general thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: They will kind of hold all the other thoughts, because there's more general to that then.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you do that by seeing that any thought, no matter how far it goes, or how particularly absorbed the focus is, is determined by this position body out there, that's subject to destruction.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why matter and body is the inter... rūpa is the same word.
[SPEAKER_01]: Often, it was interchangeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would refer to as matter as the matter of your body.
[SPEAKER_01]: We refer to rūpa.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Kāyā.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, inconceivable, there's no rūpa.
[SPEAKER_01]: And often that's the rūpa you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: But not that, not the actual rūpa, because the actual rūpa is inaccessible.
[SPEAKER_01]: The four elements, inaccessible.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's the closest proximity, as I was talking, in relation to, like, oh, these four bodies.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it was often referred to with the same word as you would refer to matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whatever, even if you have thoughts of confusion, you can't make it all up.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can think that, while this body is positioned here as such, determining your ability to think that in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that body is subject to destruction, and you know that.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the beginning, you might have to think about it more, but after a while, it just becomes implicit in that image of that body, which means your mindfulness gets established quicker, more proper, more skilled.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not about changing what has arisen, it's just recognizing the inherent undermining structure of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's undermining.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't access it directly.
[SPEAKER_01]: That which undermines you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you would, means you would be undermining it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It wouldn't be undermining you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's always below your feet, undermining you.
[SPEAKER_01]: To recognize that, means, well, you're not going to hold to anything that's being undermined.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you also realize, well, actually, yeah, I was not supposed to hold to this, at all, from the start.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it was never yours to begin with.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because
[SPEAKER_01]: If it were yours, it wouldn't have been undermined.
[SPEAKER_00]: And though I'm, I'm always there when I'm turning the body or being mindful of the body, by recognizing the nature of the body as subject to destruction.
[SPEAKER_00]: You include that, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you can never include directly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't, oh, me, I'm subject to this.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's that it kind of slides somewhere else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, what you're thinking is your sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can only uproot it indirectly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, oh, there is me in this general experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm sitting here, I'm breathing, I'm doing this, I'm doing that, while this seated body remains on the chair, fully subject to destruction.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, that self that you feel will be experienced as not-self.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why automatically...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you recognize correctly impermanence and suffering, you don't then do, oh, so this is my not-self.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, your experience as a whole is automatically the experience of not-self.
[SPEAKER_01]: You do that long enough, you will recognize that it's... that's what not-self is.
[SPEAKER_01]: By recognizing what's really not-self, well, you'll stop holding a view of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you become satipaṭṭhāna, who is free from ātavāda, which is not recognizing what actually not-self is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for as long as you see the not-self in front of you, it means, ah, you excluded your sense of self, ah, which means that's not not-self.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you do it, it's just what you said.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you... general experiences or whatever you're doing, I'm sitting here talking, whatever else, while my body, while this material body is seated, completely subject to distraction from any direction, and I absolutely cannot even foresee it happening.
[SPEAKER_01]: I just know that it's subject to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Automatically, whatever I do, while I have that perception established, will be non-self.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is exactly... See how hard it is, because it's not that hard, once you recognize it, then you know what to look for, if you have the utterance of another explaining it, sufficiently done.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can see why nobody can become an arahant and live in a sotāpanna by accident.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't open it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, many people can do this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, you see this subject.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can't do it long enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can accidentally do it once or twice or three times.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can't accidentally repeat it thousands of times, which is the number of times most likely required for somebody to recognize that as a principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why the effort, manly effort, manly strength, manly, like, repetition and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what that... that's what practice is about.
[SPEAKER_01]: Recognizing what you're supposed to discern, and then keep doing it, and keep doing it, and keep doing it, without somebody telling you that you're supposed to do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's inconceivable to do it thousands of times.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, you can't stumble upon it by a chance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, that was a fortunate night.
[SPEAKER_01]: I just... it came so upon just like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It all happened.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm so lucky.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't work like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it did, it's because you spent the whole night doing this work.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I've done it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And for that very reason, it cannot be taken away.
[SPEAKER_01]: It didn't come through any external circumstance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not given.
[SPEAKER_01]: Cannot be taken away.
[SPEAKER_01]: Recognized as already there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And because it's already there, it has nothing to do with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why we refer to it as an ancient path.
[SPEAKER_01]: They just, like, revealed it again.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it was there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if it weren't there, the escape from what's there would not be possible.